[
  {
    "question": "What type of market MOST efficiently supplies a product with very high fixed costs?",
    "a": "government-created monopoly",
    "b": "oligopoly",
    "c": "perfect competition",
    "d": "monopolistically competitive market",
    "e": "natural monopoly",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following market structures has fewest barriers to entry?",
    "a": "government monopoly",
    "b": "natural monopoly",
    "c": "monopolistic competition",
    "d": "oligopoly",
    "e": "monopsony",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "On what basis does perfect price discrimination set prices?",
    "a": "total income",
    "b": "willingness to pay",
    "c": "scarcity",
    "d": "opportunity cost",
    "e": "diminishing returns to scale",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following relationships is TRUE of cartels but not monopolies?",
    "a": "marginal revenue exceeds marginal costs",
    "b": "total revenue is less than total costs",
    "c": "marginal revenue equals marginal costs",
    "d": "total revenue equals total costs",
    "e": "total revenue exceeds total costs",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following characteristics does an oligopoly have?",
    "a": "It is more efficient than a free market.",
    "b": "It is prohibited by government regulation.",
    "c": "It has very high barriers to entry.",
    "d": "It offers price transparency.",
    "e": "It produces higher prices than a monopoly.",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What action is MOST likely to destabilize a cartel?",
    "a": "lowering output",
    "b": "creating international embargos",
    "c": "reducing the number of firms",
    "d": "raising prices",
    "e": "raising output",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which market type can be more efficient than perfect competition?",
    "a": "government-created monopoly",
    "b": "highly competitive market",
    "c": "monopolistic competition",
    "d": "natural monopoly",
    "e": "oligopoly",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "For which market structure is marginal revenue constant?",
    "a": "government-created monopoly",
    "b": "perfect competition",
    "c": "natural monopoly",
    "d": "monopolistic competition",
    "e": "oligopoly",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following policies facilitates monopoly?",
    "a": "anti-trust regulations",
    "b": "rent controls",
    "c": "patent and copyright law",
    "d": "international trade tariffs",
    "e": "high personal income tax",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "A firm faces a demand curve with a slope of -3. Which of the following answer choices BEST describes this firm?",
    "a": "It witnesses diminishing returns to scale.",
    "b": "It exists in a perfectly competitive market.",
    "c": "It earns high fixed costs.",
    "d": "It has increasing marginal costs.",
    "e": "It has market power.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which oligopoly action has the GREATEST impact on welfare outcomes?",
    "a": "enter the market",
    "b": "raise prices",
    "c": "maximize profits",
    "d": "restrict output",
    "e": "have market power",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which market is most receptive to legislation, regulation, and public ownership?",
    "a": "natural gas",
    "b": "paperback books",
    "c": "utilities",
    "d": "vitamins",
    "e": "energy balls",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following actions is LEAST likely to increase a firm’s market power?",
    "a": "buying over a competitor",
    "b": "obtaining a patent",
    "c": "raising output",
    "d": "differentiating their products",
    "e": "increasing prices",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements describes a perfectly competitive market?",
    "a": "Producers make economic profits.",
    "b": "A firm faces a perfect elasticity of demand.",
    "c": "The marginal revenue curve is downwards sloping.",
    "d": "Consumers earn zero surplus.",
    "e": "Producers possess market power.",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following situations leads to monopoly formation?",
    "a": "low supply",
    "b": "no market power",
    "c": "diminishing marginal returns",
    "d": "high barriers to entry",
    "e": "high prices",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What MAIN function does the Sherman Anti-Trust Act have?",
    "a": "allowing for free trade",
    "b": "helping create monopolies",
    "c": "resolving externalities",
    "d": "promoting competitiveness",
    "e": "reducing consumer surplus",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements describes perfect price discrimination?",
    "a": "Marginal revenue is less than in a competitive market.",
    "b": "There is some deadweight loss.",
    "c": "The firm’s marginal revenue curve is the market demand curve.",
    "d": "The firm supplies more than it did in a non-competitive market.",
    "e": "Consumer surplus is maximized.",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is price discrimination UNLIKE a price floor?",
    "a": "It decreases consumer surplus.",
    "b": "It is illegal.",
    "c": "It is socially inefficient.",
    "d": "It occurs under perfect competition.",
    "e": "It increases social welfare.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following goods or services is MOST heavily regulated?",
    "a": "semiconductors",
    "b": "lasers",
    "c": "utilities",
    "d": "rackets",
    "e": "food delivery",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what market structure is production MOST centralized?",
    "a": "monopsony",
    "b": "monopoly",
    "c": "oligopoly",
    "d": "monopolistic competition",
    "e": "perfect competition",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What incentive do all monopolies face?",
    "a": "forming a cartel",
    "b": "restricting production",
    "c": "lowering prices",
    "d": "lowering social welfare",
    "e": "hiring more workers",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor drives inefficiency in monopolistic competition?",
    "a": "Goods are differentiated.",
    "b": "Price exceeds marginal cost.",
    "c": "Firms possess market power.",
    "d": "Firms earn no economic profit.",
    "e": "Marginal revenue equals marginal cost.",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following equations is TRUE in a monopolistically competitive market?",
    "a": "AVC = MC",
    "b": "TR > TC",
    "c": "MR < MC",
    "d": "P > MC",
    "e": "MR > MC",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following markets is NOT a monopolistically competitive market?",
    "a": "calendars",
    "b": "adaptors",
    "c": "aircraft",
    "d": "cereal",
    "e": "coats",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following markets would MOST likely practice price discrimination?",
    "a": "an oligopoly",
    "b": "a cartel",
    "c": "perfect competition",
    "d": "monopolistic competition",
    "e": "a monopoly",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What prerequisite enables monopolistic competition?",
    "a": "Firms are limited in number.",
    "b": "Firms do not possess market power.",
    "c": "Firms cannot enter and exit freely.",
    "d": "The goods require high fixed costs.",
    "e": "The goods are differentiated.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What MAIN attribute promotes competition in monopolistically competitive markets?",
    "a": "They lack barriers to entry.",
    "b": "They sell differentiated products.",
    "c": "They make economic profits.",
    "d": "They have downward-sloping demand curves.",
    "e": "They maximize total welfare.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "What outcome MUST result under oligopoly?",
    "a": "decreased producer surplus",
    "b": "increased total surplus",
    "c": "cartel formation",
    "d": "tragedy of the commons",
    "e": "higher deadweight loss",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Unlike a firm in perfect competition, what phenomenon do firms in monopolistic competition face?",
    "a": "maximized total surplus",
    "b": "maximized total profits",
    "c": "positive economic profits",
    "d": "a downward-sloping demand curve",
    "e": "barriers to entry",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a cartel, in economic terms?",
    "a": "a natural monopoly supported by government regulation",
    "b": "a monopolistically competitive market becoming an oligopoly",
    "c": "multiple suppliers cooperating and behaving like a monopoly",
    "d": "a perfectly competitive market after government intervention",
    "e": "an oligopoly joining a monopoly to create a single, unified product",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  }
]

